Software engineering radio episode 40
interview with Werner Vogels.
Welcome SE Radio listeners to this new
episode of Software Engineering Radio.
This is another one of our interview
episodes. This time we are talking to
Werner Vogels. He is the CTO, the Chief
Technology Officer of Amazon. You
probably all know Amazon from the
perspective of the customer, of the user
of the system for which Werner is
responsible ultimately.
Um in this episode we're going to talk
about the other perspective, what you
have to do in order to make systems on
the scale of Amazon scalable, perform
well, and as reliable as is necessary.
Werner is an authority on building
scalable and robust distributed systems,
and he also has a web log where you can
read about his thoughts and his insights
on this topic. And it is at all things
distributed.com. We'll put this into the
show notes. We are really glad to have
Werner on the podcast. You don't get the
chance too often to talk to people who
have built systems on the scale of
Amazon. So we are really really happy to
to be able to talk to him. Again, we
have recorded this interview at the JAOO
conference 2006 in Aarhus, Denmark. And
you might hear some of the background
noise of the exhibition floor, but again
I think it's quite acceptable quality.
Have fun. Werner, why don't you explain
a little a little bit about your
personal background and your job and
what you do at Amazon?
Okay, so I'm um
I'm the Chief Technology Officer at
Amazon as well as the uh
uh Vice President for Worldwide
Architecture, which makes me
uh responsible for let's architectural
coherence throughout
all of Amazon's systems as well as,
I think the typical role of a CTO is to
represent the technology side towards
the business
and the business side towards
technology. So, you have to be able to
be
a very strong technologist, but you have
to be able to explain and take ideas
from the business side and and know how
technology what the role is that
technology should play in there.
Um, so how how I got here was, um,
so for 10 years or more than 10 years, I
was a
um
a research scientist at Cornell
University,
uh, specialized in
large-scale enterprise systems, in
building very very scalable, highly
reliable systems, at least the the
algorithms that that you need for for
that.
Um, and and along the time um, you know,
we had our own companies,
uh, transferred technology out of
academia into industry and I played a
role in that.
And as such at one moment, the
it was a
a good moment to transfer into industry.
Mhm.
So, I guess most of our listeners
probably know Amazon from from the
customer's perspective, from buying
books and CDs and stuff. So, how would
you characterize the systems that you
that you use at Amazon? Obviously, they
have to be scalable, but there are
probably other characteristics that are
interesting to talk about.
Yeah, so,
uh, I I think first thing to realize is
that Amazon is,
uh, is may look to some of our buying
customers as just a a a web store, but
in reality, it's a technology platform.
Mhm.
Um, so what what what does that mean? It
means that,
uh, it's it's on one hand an e-commerce
platform where,
um, many customers um, buy products but
also where a large of our customer
segment that is sellers actually sell
their goods. So, about 28%
of the
articles that are being sold on Amazon
are not sold by Amazon itself but by
third parties.
Um so, we had to transform the Amazon
application into
a data integration platform that could
do these kind of marketplace
businesses.
And then we had to after that transform
it into a web services environment
because we wanted to open up
all these data that was in this platform
all the product data as well as all the
community attributed data such as
reviews and lists and things like that.
We wanted to open that up for the larger
community to use.
So, that is what I call more the the
data integration side of the Amazon
platform and on the other hand there's
the the services integration side which
is mainly used by large enterprise
partners such as Target, Bombay, NBA,
and other large websites who run their
websites or we run the websites for them
but powered by Amazon technology through
through the use of the Amazon enterprise
services.
So, how would you define scalability in
in your context?
Oh, for us scalability as first of all
scalability is extremely important to us
because we
we grow over many dimensions and it's
not just a matter of
you know, having more customers but in
general your data sets grow, the number
of requests grow,
memory usage grows, number of databases,
number of developers. So, there's
there's many accesses in daily life to
scalability next to the just the pure
technical one.
So,
but if we come back to the pure
technical one,
I've given a definition in the past that
if you add resources to a system, the
scalable a system is scalable that if
you add resources to a system, then the
performance should improve.
As you
in relation to the resources that you've
added to it, you know? Um
Which which basically means that if you
want to see an equivalent improvement in
performance giving the resources that
you've added. Now, many algorithms,
especially those in the in the area of
distributed systems and fault tolerance,
do not allow you for such a nice linear
scalability.
So, that is one side of scalability.
Sometimes you have to add resources to
it because
you want to achieve redundancy or fault
tolerance. Well, in that case, the
system is scalable if
when you add those resources, the
performance does not deteriorate. It
stays stays stable. And of course, then
there is a number a number of other
important parts to scalability. You
know, you must be able to deal with
heterogeneity because if your systems
grow, it's obvious that you will get a
heterogeneous hardware. And I don't mean
different vendors, but I mean more
faster machines, machines with more
memory. And if your software is really
built for homogeneous environment, you
obviously are going to run into problems
there. Um other things around
scalability is you know, the larger
things grow, um the larger the systems
become, the higher is the probability
for seeing some continuous failures
happening,
which means that you have to have
resilience built into your system from
the start. You have to realize that if
systems scale, then that there will be
they will be failing all the time. Any
some component will fail at any time.
So, your systems have to be resilient to
that. And then, there's two two last
aspects, I think, to availability to
scalability.
Uh one is that systems need to be able
to scale
um with reduced human involvement. So,
if you need 10 people
um to manage 100 machines, if you then
go to 1,000 machines, you shouldn't go
to 100 people. Actually, I believe that
you can use the same 10 people to uh to
manage the 1,000 machines. And to be
honest, in a really scalable systems,
you should these you should your system
should be architected such that you
would only need one or two for tens of
thousands of machines
um because many of these uh many of the
management can be should can and should
be automated.
And then, the last part around
scalability is that of uh that
your your scalability techniques should
be cost-effective. Meaning that if your
system grows over time, yeah, you should
be able to exploit that larger volume
and the larger scale that you have
um
to make sure that services that are
offered are offered, you know,
the the unit of work actually costs
less.
Yeah.
I I heard people from Sun, I think, talk
about the problem of energy consumption
in big uh computing centers. So, one
aspect of scalability could also be the
amount of energy that is used. Is that
something you're kind of thinking about?
Is it a problem for you?
Absolutely. I think uh anybody that runs
large data centers is uh one one part of
your cost is power. And it's knowing
knowing that electricity um
the way that traditional electricity
electrical systems are built is that
there is a significant loss
of power uh during transfer.
Um
I don't know the numbers for for Amazon,
but I've seen them in other places where
um they may lose at
may lose as much as 50 to to 60% of the
energy
um
along the way um just by by loss of
electrical components. Uh now, I I'm not
going to say that those are the numbers
for Amazon because I don't know them. I
but these are numbers that I've heard
say otherwise. So,
pure in terms of of energy consumption,
um you know, if you could just reduce
that by half by having more efficient
circuits, absolutely. Yeah. And and I
think um actually what you referred to
was um
uh a presentation I think by the Google
guys at um at the Intel Developer Forum.
be, yeah.
Um where they actually pointed towards
um the inefficiency of power supplies on
on commodity servers.
Mhm.
Um
Now, I don't think Amazon's situation is
as bad as that the Google guys uh
assume. We we don't use commodity
um uh white box hardware like probably
they do. Mhm.
Uh so, we we already have better power
supplies, but it's clear that uh power
supplies is one of those entry points
into an an architecture that could be
vastly improved with respect to uh power
efficiency.
Mhm.
So, which kinds of technologies do you
use or do you prefer? I mean, um
you know, are you a Java guy or .NET guy
or what's what's the kind of
architectural technology you use at
Amazon?
Well, well, actually we use none of the
above.
That's what I expected, yeah.
No, so so there's a long history behind
Amazon. Amazon started off as being
having one application server talking to
a database in the back end and those
databases grew and and the application
server front end grew bigger and bigger
and
um there was more uh that particular
application was actually written in C++.
Mhm.
Um
And so, that application grew and many
of the content was actually written in a
special homegrown language.
Um
but after 4 5 years, there was clearly
an end of life of that architecture and
then we switched to
um having building another
uh application container that that would
be that would drive our service-oriented
architecture internally. So, internally
we moved
we split up all the databases into small
parts and around each part we we located
the the business functionality or the
the
the code that that operates on that data
and made sure that the only way that
that a data could be accessed was
through a services interface.
Mhm.
Um
So, coming back so the the front-end app
um the one that actually constructs the
web pages for you
um is partly written in C++ in doing
request management and and and things
like that. And then around that inside
that has a a Pearl
Pearl Mason environment to
actually build the content.
Mhm.
So, from that application container lots
of requests go out. If you hit the
gateway page it often does talks to
somewhere between 100 and 150 different
services uh to to retrieve the content
to to build the page with. Um so, that
is so there's a lot of C++ and Java
being done
within Amazon, but we also look at
newer languages such as Ruby, Erlang,
and and quite a few other techniques are
being investigated whether or not they
they they can be useful for Amazon. But,
we're not stuck with one particular
approach. There's some places where we
do use J2EE containers. Um but in this
case actually
we just use JBoss, but we use it in the
in the simplest version possible just
only the container with the JMX kernel
Mhm.
uh in some places, but no none of the
extended transactional bean stuff and
things like that.
Mhm.
And is that
I mean, is this just you your your
philosophy to build some of these things
yourselves, you have it under control,
or do you think there is I mean,
probably Uh there is specific technical
reasons why things like J2EE or for that
matter, I don't know, .NET Windows
Communication Foundation or something
isn't isn't what you want to use.
Well, maybe maybe if you would want to
start from scratch again today,
that would be you you might come to
different conclusion. Um
but our our own history has shown that
many of the third-party technologies
that we've used actually
um
are are hard to scale at the size of
Amazon.
Mhm.
Um especially
those technologies that have to do with
um
you know, the communication
infrastructure and things like that.
Repeatedly we've run into problems with
with those technologies that they work
well up up to a certain scale and that
is also clear what the vendors tell us,
you know, until that point and not
further.
Yeah.
And Amazon is such a so outlier in terms
of its scale, none of the vendors is
really interested in investing
in investing in actually scaling scaling
up their technology. If such a thing
would be possible.
So, in many cases
um
it's
we are just being forced by just by
forces of nature.
In other places we do it consciously
because especially where it goes
about um
performance, availability,
um
and and cost efficiency. Those are all
those are three things the three drivers
of the overall architecture that you
really want to have good control over.
Mhm.
Um
if if our website goes down for let's
say 15 minutes or 20 minutes and then we
have to turn around and have to say,
um
you know, this was company X's fault
Yeah.
because, you know, they gave us that
that technology but we didn't really
know we don't really know what's inside,
we don't know what the bugs are but it
came round to to bite us. That's that's
another situation you want to have. I'm
I'm not saying that Amazon
technology is more or less bug-free than
commercial technology, but it's clear
that you want to have control over that.
You want to be able to debug it. And you
know, during Q4 with millions of people
banging on your door during the holiday
season, you don't want to have long
phone calls with for example Oracle
to fix a particular problem. Now, Oracle
has been an extremely good partner of us
and and we continue to to use them in
all sorts of places. So, they're
actually more or less an example, but
um
there's there's many other vendors where
we've had this these accidents with and
we we try to avoid them.
Mhm. And in your presentation this
morning and for our listeners we're at
the Jao conference in Denmark actually.
In your keynote you you you said
something that I found quite interesting
and that was that
like you don't like middleware because
they're frameworks and not tools.
Can you elaborate on that a little bit?
Okay, there was one line in in kind of
things which are still challenges for
Amazon.
Yeah.
And it's not and that has to do with I
think uh
there's experiences that are built for
me beyond Amazon also. Um
often if you take one middleware
package, you get a sort of lock-in from
a vendor. Yeah? They have chosen
software patterns around their service
or around the software that they offer
often in a way that you can only use
their middleware.
Mhm.
Yeah? Now, ev- everyone that has in all
sorts of realism had to build a real
application knows that there's no single
vendor that can give you everything.
Yeah.
Uh
so, you might want to use packages from
three or four different middleware
vendors. Well, it's very hard to get
them to work together.
Um and so, what I say there is that you
know, these frameworks uh you often can
only use one framework at a time. So, if
a middleware forces you to use their
framework, often you're stuck. Yeah?
So, you need to have one event loop for
doing your messaging. You need to have
another event loop because of your your
data persistence provider. And then
another one for your Ajax stuff and such
things become quickly rather complex.
Now,
if middleware would be really available
in smaller components
more as tools
Yeah.
than as frameworks, that would get me
that I think a lot of developers would
make it would make it a lot easier to
mix and match different middleware
technologies.
Um so,
since we're talking about middleware
technologies and and the problems of
integrating them, I mean
web services claim that they are
interoperable. Do you have any specific
experience there? I personally am quite
skeptical there, but um so, what's your
opinion there?
Well, you know, in in essence, you know,
it's it's not that hard to just send
some XML over the wire.
Obviously, yes.
Both sides agree on what that XML means.
Yeah. Yeah.
And whether that's a schema or the WSDL
file or or whatever, I think that's
that's not too hard. Um I think where
most people's skepticism comes from is
from the extended
WS stack. Um that seems to be able seems
to want to solve all distributed systems
problems again, but now for for web web
services. Now, that's great for some of
your vendor documentation. Um
but but in essence, I don't think it
helps the idea around service
orientation. Now,
I'm I'm I'm I'm not going to make um you
know, break a
a lance for for for
promote either SOAP or REST style
interfaces. In Amazon Web Services, we
offer both.
Mhm.
Um and if you look at the statistic, it
it appears that there is about uh 20% 20
to 30% of the calls come in over the
SOAP interfaces and the 70% comes in
over REST. Now, that has nothing to do
actually
um with either technology.
It turns out that if you analyze analyze
this,
um those uh developers that are using
the SOAP interfaces
in general use Java or .NET. They
consume uh the WSDL file, which creates
then a whole bunch of remote objects for
them, and that's how they use it. Um the
developers that use the the the REST
interface are actually developers that
that have picked up a PHP or a Pearl
library that encapsulates those
interfaces. Now, from the outside,
whether it's a whole bunch of remote
objects or whatever it is, the PHP um
Pearl libraries, um you still get some
sort of procedural object-oriented
interface to Amazon, and and developers,
to be honest, at that level don't care.
They absolutely don't care what goes on
the wire. They just want to get their
job done. Now,
um of course, this is a more this is a
a simpler approach to doing uh web web
web services. I believe you can very
quickly start doing your web services.
You don't need to buy into some sort of
major revolutionary approach. You know,
you can start off with thinking, "Well,
you know, what if I would just do my
inventory level of product X as a
service?" And you could even do that
internally within your server within
your company. That takes one developer
to do that, and then you let it run free
after that. Let's see whether the other
developers in your company can do some
mixing and matching with that service
that you've developed. Um
there's there's a lot of there's a lot
to be gained there. Now, for us, web
services was really important because we
wanted to build uh an open community
around Amazon. And for that, web
services seemed to be the ideal
technology because it's simple for
people to use.
Right, so you you're you're using them
on the perimeter, basically, on the
outside, but not internally very much.
not using web services as such on the
inside. We you we have a
service-oriented architecture
internally. That means all data is
encapsulated by services and the only
way to get access to that functionality
or to the data is through the service
interface. And actually we describe the
service interfaces in WSDL.
Mhm.
Um but we use uh our own homegrown
transport mechanisms and and
encapsulation mechanisms there. So, even
though they're not using XML, you might
still say they're services or even web
services.
Yeah.
Um
uh it's it's it's you know, it's
fine-grained bickering about this.
Yeah.
Um and I think you know, anything that
that produces a lot of hype before it
delivers any real implementations is
bound to run into problems.
Yeah.
Um
but as such I think web services can can
start to do a lot for people, but you
know, take it step-by-step
Mhm.
and and build some good stuff there.
So, you mentioned that you you're using
an SOA internally,
um which of course prompts the question,
uh what you think is the characteristic
properties of SOAs? Because this is a
term that's really not very well
defined, I think. So, uh
Yeah, so for I can only mention it
within the context of Amazon, of course.
Yeah, of course, yes.
Yeah. Um and for Amazon, services mean
that they're the independent units that
deliver specific functionality within
Amazon. Um
it's also how Amazon is organized in
terms of teams. So,
uh in general, if you have a new a new
business idea or a new problem that we
want to solve, you create a small team.
Um we would like those teams not to be
uh not to be larger than let's say eight
to 10 people.
Mhm.
Because after that, communication within
the team uh actually goes exponentially.
Uh and we call those teams two-pizza
teams. You know, the team should not be
larger than what you can feed off two
pizzas.
Yeah? Um and so, teams are small. Uh and
team gets uh
gets the assignment to solve something
to solve and to solve it as a service.
Yeah?
Uh for example, uh
this is something we went through last
year. We have We have all these books
scanned in and we have all these texts
of these books such that we could do
search inside the book. Um there was a
popular uh
popular technique but uh a popular
service that that we offered but there's
so much more that you can do once you
have the text of books.
Mhm.
So,
uh so one of the things you know one of
the new ideas was well you know what can
we do in terms of analyzing the books
analyzing text such that we can build
sort of new relationships between books.
Um
Um and that team then went off and
created something
used statistical improbable phrases find
phrases in a book that are unique for
the book. Then find other books that
have the same unique phrase and then
make relationships for them. And such
in that way your customers can actually
find different products now on the side.
And the way we new relationships that
that were unknown
before that now. So, a team takes that
idea goes off and has all the authority
to build that particular service in any
way that they see fit. Then you know the
outcome we integrated do in in into the
website we do extensive
uh sort of AB testing you know with and
without and see what the impact is and
do relentless measurements around there.
And then and then take it from there.
Now,
the way that we can do all these things
in parallel is because the output of
that is a is a service.
Mhm.
And um it really meets the needs of our
really sort of agile development and I
don't mean that in terms of you know the
official agile development I mean more
as the common agile word.
Yeah.
Um
You know to really have fast time to
market be independent
Uh it's important that the
infrastructure around it around these
services allow you to to build these
services very fast. Yes, so that you can
do deployment easily, you can do
um instrumentation for monitoring, uh
tracking, all these kind of things
because the infrastructure helps you
build services this quickly.
So, I guess you have your own kind of
little tools that help people come up
with services that are compliant to your
internal guidelines like for monitoring
or deployability or things.
Um so, we um well, they're not little
tools. Uh at at at Amazon scale, these
things grow big. Uh take for example the
whole
um
uh the whole build process plus
deployment process. We have two big
systems there mainly for managing
dependencies and then being able to do
it the deployment of of a system like
that.
Um so, it's pretty complex because of
course, you want all the right tools to
be deployed on on a new services box.
Yeah, and that means not only the code
that works for
um your particular application but also
all the monitoring code and all the
other some licensing stuff and all the
other things that need to be present at
at a node if it's going to be deployed
in the Amazon network.
Yeah.
Uh so, there's lots of tools around
there also homegrown grow um and
developed over time. Um The thing is
that I've seen almost every other
company have a similar style of problems
and everybody has a homegrown system
that does this for them.
Um
one one thing to realize is that um
with
uh with EC2, which is our elastic
compute cloud
um
uh
offering in web services, you already
get a bit of a glimpse about the
technologies that we using internally
for development. Um
so, there, you know, your your your
output of your deployment process is a
virtual machine image, which you then
can use EC2 to to start any number of
those
dynamically.
Um, and and but very important in the
overall infrastructure of Amazon is
indeed our monitoring and
performance management
because if you have such a large chaos
of services,
now you need to be able to find out what
are the dependencies between services on
the time you need to be able to look to
inspect their performance, not only now
but historically.
And you need to be able to have very
good tools, of course, to debug such a
very large distributed system.
So, um,
before you you said that you have your
own technologies, but you could use some
of the J2EE or .NET stuff. So, I guess
the really important thing is not the
technology, but rather a set of
architectural patterns or guidelines or
styles or whatever you like to call this
in order to build
kind of system that you have to build.
So, can you elaborate a little bit on on
things like stateful, stateless, RPC
versus message-based, you know, these
some of these of these characteristics
are are are
So, so important within Amazon is
definitely loosely coupled.
If there is one of those
high-level buzzwords, I think loosely
coupled is one that does well within
Amazon. Um,
I think, you know, if
there is, you know, development process,
there is something which we call
actually working from the customer
backwards. So,
if you have a large environment like
Amazon,
the trick is to continue to focus on the
kind of value that you want to deliver
for your customer
and not get too much hooked up into all
sorts of fancy technology or
infrastructure that you can develop.
So, what we do is
we we force developers or or teams like
that to focus on the particular value
they have to deliver for the customer.
And then use a process that is called
from working from the customer
backwards. So you kind of go through an
inverse process instead of developing
technology first and then figuring out
what kind of problems you want to solve
with it and and do
this works really well. The first thing
that someone that starts such a service
has to write is for example a press
release.
Yeah.
So the first thing to write not
necessarily that has to go out to the
press but the idea is that in the press
in the press release in general you
pretty clearly describe what is the
functionality that you're going to
offer.
So you work backwards from that. You
take all the other steps
just to make sure that you end up with a
design that is as minimal as possible.
Yeah.
Simplicity I think is key.
If you really want want to build very
large distributed systems, the only way
that you're capable of managing them is
if to keep things simple. And you can
keep things simple by making sure that
there are no hidden requirements and
hidden dependencies and all these kind
of things in your design and really
cutting the technology as minimal to
exactly what you need to solve the
particular problem for the customer.
Mhm.
Yeah, that's
that's an interesting take that somehow
goes against some of the hype driven
vendor driven technology
Well I think we all love technology. You
know we would do nothing
Nobody I think all engineers that I know
the the the coolest thing you would do
is just build your own level your own
infrastructure your own level of
middleware and then all sorts of things
and then you know and all for maybe some
future use of you know oh that would be
really cool to have.
Unfortunately I think
it doesn't help a company
you create
all sorts of layers of extreme high
complexity that the only thing that can
really happen to them is that they fail.
Yeah. Yeah.
Uh so, in terms of the other things
actually that you ask, you know,
stateful versus stateless, RPC, message
base, things like that. Um
I think if you look at large system and
the scalability scalability of those
large system,
it's all centered around state
management.
Mhm.
Um so, uh at Amazon we have a number of
these very large storage engines. Um S3
on the outside is for example
one of them.
Yeah.
Uh but we have a number internally also
that are really focused on building
delivering very highly available
storage, infinite storage to developers.
Um
and so,
the essence of some of the operations
are that they're stateless by
themselves.
Yeah.
And for others it's just state they're
they are stateful, but um there aren't
really that many operations that are
stateful in an environment like this.
Most of them
Yeah.
take uh some customer ID or maybe take
some session ID um
to look at uh you know, some services
that work maybe on giving you
recommendations based on the things that
you did in this session.
Yeah.
But it's not that we then suddenly start
keeping track of that. We were keeping
track of that anyway.
Mhm. Yeah.
Uh so, many of them
data base basically.
in It's in some storage. It's in It's in
some service.
Yeah.
Some service the the what is it? The
most recent clicked uh web page service
or something like that.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Um that would give you this particular
information. Um
so, there isn't that much so, most of
our services are pretty stateless in
that sense. But I think that goes for
most of the web
e-commerce style applications.
Yeah.
And of course, once you get into uh a
series of checkout steps, there is state
associated with that.
process more
But, you know, then that becomes more
workflow orientation than than it's a
web page environment. Yeah.
Can you
something else I remember from your
presentation this morning
the CAP theorem? I think that's also
very interesting and maybe worth briefly
elaborating on.
Okay, so this morning I tried to explain
you know, what is what is some of the
core problems that I think everyone that
has to do large scale state management
have to deal with. So, the CAP theorem
is something that was
um
dubbed by Eric Brewer who used to run
Ink to me and is now back at being a
professor at in in Berkeley.
Um is it something that he posed in a
presentation to the PotC community which
is a distributed systems theoretician
community.
Um
So, the statement there was that there
are these three properties of systems.
Um One is partitionability meaning that
whether or not
a system can have a number of nodes on
one side of a network partition and then
all the other set of nodes on another
side of the network partition and while
they can see the small groups, they
can't see everyone.
Uh so, that is basically
partitionability. And then there is
consistency.
That's the C and then there is A it's
availability and the P for partitioning.
Consistency means that if I if I write a
value and then I read the value, then I
get the same value back. Yeah? Uh there
was a few conditions on the partition on
the partitions that it is not possible
or that there is a small
chance that that would happen. On the
other hand, there's the highly available
stuff meaning that, you know, sometimes
you cannot
you can always write to it.
Mhm.
Yeah. Um
but you might not be able to read or you
might not be able or sometimes the
system will say no, I can't write
because I want to keep things
consistent.
Yeah.
Now, so anyway, coming back to this the
there's these of these three properties,
you can only always get two.
Mhm.
Yeah.
And in reality, systems like Amazon are
always partitionable because they're
always relying on on the network.
Um so, that almost means that you have
to choose for your system, for your data
system to be either highly consistent,
meaning that whatever I write to it, I
can always read it back,
Mhm.
or to be highly available, which means
that under certain circumstances, the
system will say no.
Mhm.
store it.
Yeah. Um and so, there's these
trade-offs uh on on both sides. And so,
it's very it's to build really scalable
systems, you have to find uh the right
overlap between choices of availability
and consistency.
Mhm. Yeah.
Okay, so before we wrap up this this
episode, I'd like to ask you what what
you think about some of the interesting
trends for distributed systems. People
might have heard about things like JBI
or SCA. So, is there anything on the
horizon, grids, whatever, that that you
think that might kind of revolutionize
distributed systems architecture?
Oh, no. No, no, no. I think actually
that we need just need to go on with
what we're doing. This morning No, this
morning I gave a long list of what I
think are very common sense distributed
systems approaches to these days. We
know a lot. We know a lot how to build
systems, and especially the systems of
medium to large scale, not really large
as in Amazon's case, and but you know,
hundreds to thousands of of of nodes. I
think
we've come a long way in in doing that,
and there's
both from academic research as well as
the research labs, as well as vendors.
There's a lot of good technologies
around caching, around heterogeneous
management,
whether they're greedy algorithms or
maybe even lazy approaches, and all
those kind of things. I think we've
we've produced quite a body of work.
Yeah.
Um what I would like to see is that that
stuff becomes more user-friendly, more
easily usable, especially the more
esoteric ones because I think there's a
lot of
a lot of things to be gained there.
Um, and and and pushing it further along
to for building really scalable systems.
Um,
I think we if you want to build really
scalable systems, you have to change
your mentality a little bit where
you almost have to approach a sort of
chaos approach. You know, where in a
probabilistic sense, things will work
well.
On average?
On No, no, not on average. We maybe even
out on the TP99 or all the way on on the
outskirts.
But that, you know,
what we've done in traditional
distributed systems techniques often is
to present a perfect world.
Yeah.
If you use this technology, it will
never go down. Well,
first of all, that's impossible to
guarantee.
But, you know, we then use all sorts of
very complex agreement technologies and
and there's all sorts of algorithms to
really almost approach this perfect
world as close as possible. Yeah.
Um, however, if you if you take a more
realistic approach and says, "Well, you
know, stuff fails all around you. Um,
that's reality. Why don't we embrace it
and go more for a sort of fast reboot or
fast recovery approach?"
On a problem with a with a decent
probabilistic
spread of your data and of your
services, you might get pretty close to
to this 100% availability without
actually doing as much effort as that
you used to do in the past. So, you
know, a more probabilistic approach to
things in terms of highly scalable
highly scalable systems, also
self-organizing.
If if if we need to get to places where,
you know, they can automatically heal,
where you have large data centers where
there is no data techs running around
anymore. Things completely lights out
and you need to have a self-healing
environment.
So, I think those are more promising
areas, I think, where we will be still
see some development in in in the coming
years.
Um on on the customer side, I you know,
I love what lots of people are doing
with with Ajax. Also, what lots of
people are doing with mixing and mashing
of different applications.
I really do hope that more more
companies will take the effort in
opening up some of their
some of just some part of their
infrastructure or some part of their
products just for people to use.
You will instantly create a whole
ecosystem around your company.
And and really your customers or your
your fans at that moment will really
surprise you with lots of new stuff.
Um so, yeah, I think those are those are
the more promising directions, I think,
for for the for the coming years.
Okay, so Warner, thanks for being on the
show and yeah,
good luck with Amazon.
Okay, thank you.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio or if you want to give
us feedback, please go to our website at
se-radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although, we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music as
well as Libsyn for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE Radio, as well as all
other episodes, is licensed under
Creative Commons license. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.